<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook V4.2//EN"
"docbookV4.2/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY ch01-Introduction SYSTEM "modules/ch01-Introduction.xml">
<!ENTITY ch02-Installation SYSTEM "modules/ch02-Installation.xml">
<!ENTITY ch03-ErraiBus SYSTEM "modules/ch03-errai-bus.xml">
<!ENTITY appendix-A-Quickstart SYSTEM "modules/appendix-A-Quickstart.xml">
]>
<book lang="en">
  <bookinfo>
    <title>Errai User Guide</title>
  </bookinfo>

  <toc></toc>

  <!---
        =====================================================
        INTRODUCTION
        =====================================================
    -->

  <chapter id="introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <section>
      <title>What is it</title>

      <para>Errai is a GWT-based framework for building rich web applications
      using next-generation web technologies. Built on-top of ErraiBus, the
      framework provides a unified federation and RPC infrastructure with
      true, uniform, asynchronous messaging across the client and
      server.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>License and EULA</title>

      <para>Errai is distributed under the terms of the the Apache License,
      Version 2.0. See<ulink url="http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0">
      the full Apache license text</ulink>.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Downloads</title>

      <para>The distribution packages can be downloaded from jboss.org <ulink
      url="http://jboss.org/errai/Downloads.html">http://jboss.org/errai/Downloads.html</ulink></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Sources</title>

      <para>The source code for this component can be found in the Errai SVN
      repository: <ulink
      url="http://anonsvn.jboss.org/repos/errai/trunk/">https://anonsvn.jboss.org/repos/errai/trunk/</ulink></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Reporting problems</title>

      <para>If you run into trouble don't hesitate to get in touch with us:
      <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>JIRA Issue Tracking: <ulink
            url="https://jira.jboss.org/jira/browse/ERRAI">https://jira.jboss.org/jira/browse/ERRAI
            </ulink></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>User Forum: <ulink
            url="http://www.jboss.org/index.html?module=bb&amp;op=viewforum&amp;f=295">http://www.jboss.org/index.html?module=bb&amp;op=viewforum&amp;f=295</ulink></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Mailing List: <ulink
            url="http://jboss.org/errai/MailingLists.html">http://jboss.org/errai/MailingLists.html</ulink></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>IRC: irc://irc.freenode.net/errai</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <!---
        =====================================================
        INSTALLATION
        =====================================================
    -->

  <chapter id="installation">
    <title>Installation</title>

    <section>
      <title>Required software</title>

      <para>Errai requires a JDK version 5 or higher and depends on Apache
      Maven to build and run the examples, and for leverging the quickstart
      utilities. <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>JDK 5: <ulink
            url="http://java.sun.com/javase/downloads/index.jsp">http://java.sun.com/javase/downloads/index.jsp</ulink></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Apache Maven: <ulink
            url="http://maven.apache.org/download.html">http://maven.apache.org/download.html</ulink></para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist> <note>
          <title>Launching maven the first time</title>

          <para>Please note, that when launching maven the first time on your
          machine, it will fetch all dependecies from a central repository.
          This may take a while, because it includes downloading large
          binaries like GWT SDK. However subsequent builds are not required to
          go through this step and will be much faster.</para>
        </note></para>
    </section>

    <section id="thedistribution">
      <title>Distribution Package</title>

      <para>Unzip the Errai download (<literal>Errai-X.Y.zip</literal>) to
      some location on your hard drive. You'll see following
      subdirectories:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><filename>doc</filename>: User guide and javadocs</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><filename>examples</filename>: Examples that are used in the
          user guide</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><filename>lib</filename>: Required libraries</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <!---
        =====================================================
        BUS
        =====================================================
    -->

  <chapter id="bus">
    <title>Errai Bus</title>

    <sect1 id="bus-intro">
      <title>What is Errai Bus?</title>

      <para>ErraiBus forms the backbone of the Errai framework's approach to
      application design. Most importantly, it provides a straight-forward
      approach to a complex problem space. Providing common APIs across the
      client and server, developers will have no trouble working with complex
      messaging scenarios from building instant messaging clients, stock
      tickers, to monitoring instruments. There's no more messing with RPC
      APIs, or unweildy AJAX or COMET frameworks. We've built it all in to
      one, consice messaging framework. It's single-paradigm, and it's fun to
      work with.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>Messaging</title>

      <para>This section covers the core messaging concepts of the ErraiBus
      messaging framework. </para>

      <sect2>
        <title>Messaging Overview</title>

        <para>It's important to understand the concept of how messaging works
        in ErraiBus. Service endpoints are given string-based names that are
        referenced by message senders. There is no difference between sending
        a message to a client-based service, or sending a message to a
        server-based service. In fact, a service of the same name may co-exist
        on both the client and the server and both will receive all messages
        bound for that service name, whether they are sent from the client or
        from the server. </para>

        <para>Services are lightweight in ErraiBus, and can be declared
        liberally and extensively within your application to provide a
        message-based infrastructure for your web application. It can be
        tempting to think of ErraiBus simply as a client-server communication
        platform, but there is a plethora of possibilities for using ErraiBus
        purely with the GWT client context, such as a way to advertise and
        expose components dynamically, to get around the lack of reflection in
        GWT. </para>

        <para>In fact, ErraiBus was originally designed to run completely
        within the client but quickly evolved into having the capabilities it
        now has today. So keep that in mind when you run up against problems
        in the client space that could benefit from runtime federation.
        </para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>MessageBuilder API</title>

        <para>The MessageBuilder is the heart of the messaging API in
        ErraiBus. It provides a fluent / builder API, that is used for
        constructing messages. All three major message patterns can be
        constructed from the MessageBuilder.</para>

        <para>Components that want to receive messages need to implement the
        MessageCallback interface.</para>

        <para>But before we dive into the details, let look at some use cases
        first.</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>Sending Messages with the Client Bus</title>

        <para>In order to send a message from a client you need to create a
        <emphasis><emphasis><filename>Message</filename></emphasis></emphasis>
        and send it through an instance of <filename>MessageBus</filename>. In
        this simple example we send it to the subject
        'HelloWorldService'.</para>

        <programlisting>    public class HelloWorld implements EntryPoint {

        // Get an instance of the MessageBus
        private MessageBus bus = ErraiBus.get();

        public void onModuleLoad() {
            Button button = new Button("Send message");

            button.addClickHandler(new ClickHandler() {

            public void onClick(ClickEvent event) {
                // Send a message to the 'HelloWorldService'.
                MessageBuilder.createMessage()
                    .toSubject("HelloWorldService")             // (1)
                    .signalling()                               // (2)
                    .noErrorHandling()                          // (3)
                    .sendNowWith(bus);                          // (4)
            });

            [...]
         }
    }</programlisting>

        <para>In the above example we build and send a message every time the
        button is clicked. Here's an explanation of what's going on as
        annotated above:</para>

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>We specify the subject we wish to send a message to. In this
            case, "HelloWorldService".</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>We indicate that we wish to only signal the service,
            meaning, that we're not sending a qualifying command to the
            service. For information on this, read the section on
            <emphasis>Protocols</emphasis>.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>We indicate that we do not want to provide an ErrorCallback
            to deal with errors for this message.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>We transmit the message by providing an instance of the
            MessageBus</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>

        <note>
          <para>An astute observer will note that access to the
          <literal>MessageBus</literal> differs within client code and server
          code. Because the client code does not run within a container,
          access to the <literal>MessageBus</literal> is statically accessed
          using the <literal>ErraiBus.get()</literal> method. The server-side
          code, conversely, runs inside a dependency container for managing
          components. It currently uses Guice as the default container, but
          will more generically support the JSR-330 specification in the
          future. </para>
        </note>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>Recieving Messages on the Server Bus / Server Services</title>

        <para>Every message has a sender and at least one receiver. A receiver
        is as it sounds--it receives the message and does something with it.
        Implementing a receiver (also referred to as a service) is as simple
        as implementing our standard MessageCallback interface, which is used
        pervasively across, both client and server code. Let's begin with
        server side component that receives messages:</para>

        <programlisting>   @Service
    public class HelloWorldService implements MessageCallback {
        public void callback(Message message) {
            System.out.println("Hello, World!");
        }
    }</programlisting>

        <para>He we declare an extremely simple service. The @Service
        annotation provides a convenient, meta-data based way of having the
        bus auto-discover and deploy the service.</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>Sending Messages with the Server Bus</title>

        <para>In the following example we extend our server side component to
        replyNow with a message when the callback method is invoked. It will
        create a message and address it to the subject
        'HelloWorldClient':</para>

        <programlisting>    @Service
    public class HelloWorldService implements MessageCallback {

        private MessageBus bus;

        @Inject
        public HelloWorldService(MessageBus bus) {
            this.bus = bus;
        }

        public void callback(CommandMessage message) {
                // Send a message to the 'HelloWorldClient'.
                MessageBuilder.createMessage()
                    .toSubject("HelloWorldClient")              // (1)
                    .signalling()                               // (2)
                    .with("text", "Hi There")                   // (3)
                    .noErrorHandling()                          // (4)
                    .sendNowWith(bus);                          // (5)
            });
        }
    }   </programlisting>

        <para>The above example shows a service which sends a message in
        response to receiving a message. Here's what's going on:</para>

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>We specify the subject we wish to send a message to. In this
            case, "HelloWorldClient". We are sending this message to all
            clients which are listening in on this subject. For information on
            how to communicate with a single client, see Section 2.6.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>We indicate that we wish to only signal the service, meaning
            that we're not sending a qualifying command to the service. For
            information on this, read the section on Protocols.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>We add a message part called "text" which contains the value
            "Hi there".</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>We indicate that we do not want to provide an ErrorCallback
            to deal with errors for this message.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>We transmit the message by providing an instance of the
            MessageBus.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>Receiving Messages on the Client Bus/ Client Services</title>

        <para>Messages can be received asynchronously and arbitriraily by
        declaring callback services within the client bus. As ErraiBus
        maintains an open COMET channel at all times, these messages are
        delivered in real time to the client as they are sent. This provides
        built-in push messaging for all client services.</para>

        <programlisting>
    public class HelloWorld implements EntryPoint {
        private MessageBus bus = ErraiBus.get();

        public void onModuleLoad() {
        [...]

        /**
        * Declare a local service to receive messages on the subject
        * "BroadcastReceiver".
        */
        bus.subscribe("BroadcastReceiver", new MessageCallback() {
            public void callback(CommandMessage message) {
                /**
                * When a message arrives, extract the "text" field and
                * do something with it
                */
                String messageText = message.get(String.class, "text");
            }
        });

        [...]
    }</programlisting>

        <para>In the above example, we declare a new client service called
        <literal>"BroadcastReceiver"</literal> which can now accept both local
        messages and remote messages from the server bus. The service will be
        available in the client to receive messages as long the client bus is
        connected and the service is not explicitly de-registered.</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>Conversations</title>

        <para>Conversations are message exchanges which are between a single
        client and a service. They are a fundmentally important concept in
        ErraiBus, since by default, a message will be broadcast to all client
        services listening on a particular channel.</para>

        <para>When you create a conversation with an incoming message, you
        ensure that the message you are sending back is received by the same
        client which sent the incoming message. A simple example:</para>

        <programlisting>   @Service
    public class HelloWorldService implements MessageCallback {

        private MessageBus bus;

        @Inject
        public HelloWorldService(MessageBus bus) {
            this.bus = bus;
        }

        public void callback(CommandMessage message) {
                // Send a message to the 'HelloWorldClient' on the client that sent us the
                // the message.
                MessageBuilder.createConversation(message)
                    .toSubject("HelloWorldClient")
                    .signalling()
                    .with("text", "Hi There! We're having a conversation!")
                    .noErrorHandling()
                    .sendNowWith(bus);
            });
        }
    }</programlisting>

        <para>Note that the only difference between the example in the
        previous section (2.4) and this is the use of the
        <filename>createConversation() </filename>method with
        <filename>MessageBuilder</filename>.</para>

        <sect3>
          <title>Single-Response Conversations / Psuedo-Synchronous
          Messaging</title>

          <para>It is possible to contruct a message and a default response
          handler as part of the MessageBuilder API. It should be noted, that
          multiple replies will not be possible and will result an exception
          if attempted. Using this aspect of the API is very useful for doing
          simple psuedo-synchronous conversive things.</para>

          <para>You can do this by specifying a
          <literal>MessageCallback</literal> using the
          <literal>repliesTo()</literal> method in the
          <literal>MessageBuilder</literal> API after specifying the error
          handling of the message.</para>

          <programlisting>MessageBuilder.createMessage()
      .toSubject("ConversationalService").signalling()
      .with("SomeField", someValue)
      .noErrorHandling()
      .repliesTo(new MessageCallback() {
           public void callback(Message message) {
               System.out.println("I received a response");
           }
      })</programlisting>

          <para>See the next section on how to build conversational services
          that can respond to such messages. </para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3>
          <title>Sender Inferred Subjects</title>

          <para>It is possible for the sender to infer, to whatever
          conversational service it is calling, what subject it would like the
          replyNow to go to. This is accomplished by utilizing the standard
          <filename>MessageParts.ReplyTo</filename> message part. Using this
          methodology for building conversations is generally
          encouraged.</para>

          <para>Consider the following client side code:</para>

          <programlisting>MessageBuilder.createMessage()
       .toSubject("ObjectService").signalling()
       .with(MessageParts.ReplyTo, "ClientEndpoint")
       .noErrorHandling().sendNowWith(bus);</programlisting>

          <para>And the conversational code on the server (for service
          <emphasis>ObjectService</emphasis>):</para>

          <programlisting>MessageBuilder.createConversation(message)
                .subjectProvided().signalling()
                .with("Records", records)
                .noErrorHandling().sendNowWith(bus);</programlisting>

          <para>In the above examples, assuming that the latter example is
          inside a service called "ObjectService" and is referencing the
          incoming message that was send in the former example, the message
          created will automatically reference the
          <filename>ReplyTo</filename> subject that was provided by the
          sender, and send the message back to the subject desired by the
          client on the client that sent the message.</para>
        </sect3>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>Broadcasting</title>

        <para>Broadcasting messages to all clients listening on a specific
        subject is quite simple and involves nothing more than forgoing use of
        the conversation API. For instance:</para>

        <programlisting>MessageBuilder.createMessage().
                 .toSubject("MessageListener")
                 .with("Text", "Hello, from your overlords in the cloud")
                 .noErrorHandling().sendNowWith(bus);</programlisting>

        <para>If sent from the server, all clients currently connected, who
        are listening to the subject <filename>"MessageListener"</filename>
        will receive the message. It's as simple as that.</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>Client-to-Client Communication</title>

        <para>Communication from one client to another client is not directly
        possible within the bus federation, by design. This isn't to say that
        it's not possible. But one client cannot see a service within the
        federation of another client. We institute this limitation as a matter
        of basic security. But many software engineers will likely find the
        prospects of such communication appealing, so this section will
        provide some basic pointers on how to go about accomplishing
        it.</para>

        <sect3>
          <title>Relay Services</title>

          <para>The essential architectural thing you'll need to do is create
          a relay service that runs on the server. Since a service advertised
          on the server is visible to all clients and all clients are visible
          to the server, you might already see where we're going with
          this.</para>

          <para>By creating a service on the server which accepts messages
          from clients, you can create a simple protocol on-top of the bus to
          enable quasi peer-to-peer communication. (We say quasi, because it
          still needs to be routed through the server)</para>

          <para>While you can probably imagine simply creating a
          broadcast-like service which accepts a message from one client and
          broadcasts it to the rest of the world, it may be less clear how to
          go about routing from one particular client to another particualr
          client, so we'll focus on that problem.</para>

          <para><emphasis role="bold">Message Routing
          Information</emphasis></para>

          <para>Every message that is sent between a local and remote (or
          server and client) buses contain session routing information. This
          information is used by the bus to determine what outbound queue's to
          use to deliver the message to their intended recipients. It is
          possible to manually specify this information to indicate to the
          bus, where you want a specific message to go.</para>

          <para>The utility class
          <filename>org.jboss.errai.bus.server.util.ServerBusUtils</filename>
          contains a utility method for extracting the String-based SessionID
          which is used to identify the message queue associated with any
          particular client. You may use this method to extract the SessionID
          from a message so that you may use it for routing. For
          example:</para>

          <programlisting>...
public void callback(Message message) {
    String sessionId = ServerBusUtils.getSessionId(message);

    // Record this sessionId somewhere.
    ...
}
...

</programlisting>

          <para>The SessionID can then be stored in a medium, say a Map, to
          cross-reference specific users or whatever identifier you wish to
          allow one client to obtain a reference to the specific ClientId of
          another client. In which case, you can then provide the SessionID as
          a MessagePart to indicate to the bus where you want the message to
          go.</para>

          <programlisting>MessageBuilder.createMessage()
    .toSubject("ClientMessageListener")
    .signalling()
    .with(MessageParts.SessionID, sessionId)
    .with("Message", "We're relaying a message!")
    .noErrorHandling().sendNowWith(bus);
</programlisting>

          <para>By providing the SessionID part in the message, the bus will
          see this and use it for routing the message to the relevant
          queue.</para>

          <para>Now you're routing from client-to-client!</para>
        </sect3>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>Remote Procedure Calls (RPC)</title>

      <para>ErraiBus supports a high-level RPC layer to make typical
      client-server RPC communication easy on top of the bus. While it is
      possible to use ErraiBus without ever using this API, you may find it to
      be a more useful and concise approach to exposing services to the
      clients.</para>

      <sect2>
        <title>Creating callable endpoints</title>

        <para>ErraiBus provides facility to making asynchronous RPC calls
        on-top of the bus archhitecture without the need to explicitly declare
        services or any specific mapping or boilerplate code. This method of
        communicating with the server is straight-forward and utilizes the
        simple <filename>RemoteCall</filename> API.</para>

        <para>Remote procedure calls can be be performed against against
        service class which has been annoted with the
        <filename>@Service</filename> annotation and the accompanying method
        which is being called has been annotated with the
        <filename>@Endpoint</filename> annotation, and the method has public
        access.</para>

        <programlisting>@Service
public class QueryService {
   private Map&lt;String, String[]&gt; dataMap;

   public QueryService() {
      setupMap();
   }

   private void setupMap() {
      dataMap = new HashMap&lt;String, String[]&gt;();
      dataMap.put("beer", new String[]{"Heineken", "Budweiser", "Hoogaarden"});
      dataMap.put("fruit", new String[]{"Apples", "Oranges", "Grapes"});
      dataMap.put("animals", new String[]{"Monkeys", "Giraffes", "Lions"});
   }

   @Endpoint
   public String[] getQuery(String queryString) {
      return dataMap.get(queryString.toLowerCase());
   }
}</programlisting>

        <para>Notice the <filename>@Endpoint </filename>annotation on the
        <filename>getQuery()</filename> method in the above figure. In this
        example, the method simply accepts a single String parameter and
        returns an array of Strings. The method can accept and return any
        serializable types that have been exposed to the bus within the rules
        of serializability as laid out in the section on <emphasis>Object
        Serialization</emphasis>.</para>

        <para>Also note that in this example, the service class is not
        required to implement the <filename>MessageCallback</filename>
        interface and is a simple POJO class.</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>Making calls</title>

        <para>Calls to RPC endpoints are made using the RemoteCall API which
        is very similar to the MessageBuilder API, with a few key differences.
        Here is some code for calling the RPC endpoint we defined in section
        3.1.</para>

        <programlisting>MessageBuilder.createCall()
           .call("QueryService")                                         // (1)
           .endpoint("getQuery", queryBox.getText())                     // (2)
           .respondTo(String[].class, new RemoteCallback&lt;String[]&gt;() {   // (3)
               public void callback(String[] resultsString) {
                   if (resultsString == null) {
                       resultsString = new String[]{"No results."};
                   }

                   /**
                    * Build an HTML unordered list based on the results.
                    */
                   StringBuffer buf = new StringBuffer("&lt;ul&gt;");
                   for (String result : resultsString) {
                       buf.append("&lt;li&gt;").append(result).append("&lt;/li&gt;");
                   }
                   results.setHTML(buf.append("&lt;/ul&gt;").toString());
               }
           })
           .noErrorHandling()
           .sendNowWith(bus);                                           // (4)</programlisting>

        <para>In this example we <emphasis role="bold"><emphasis
        role="bold">(1)</emphasis></emphasis> send a call to the
        <filename>"QueryService"</filename> class with <emphasis
        role="bold">(2)</emphasis> the endpoint
        <filename>"getQuery"</filename>, which is the name of the method which
        we annotated, along with the parameter we which to pass to the method.
        Note that you can send as many parameters as you want as the
        <filename>endpoint()</filename> method accepts varargs
        parameter.</para>

        <para>Then <emphasis role="bold">(3)</emphasis> we declare a
        <filename>RemoteCallback</filename> to handle the response back from
        the server. We declare the response type to be that of
        <filename>String[]</filename> to correlate with the return type of the
        endpoint on the server and fill in handling code for the response. In
        this case we output an HTML unordered list manually.</para>

        <para>Finally <emphasis role="bold">(4)</emphasis> we send the
        call.</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>Serialization</title>

      <para>Serialization on the ErraiBus supports serialization within the
      same scope and limitations as the default GWT RPC serialization rules.
      In order to expose your domain objects to the bus so they can be
      exported across the bus, you must annotate them with the
      <filename>org.jboss.errai.bus.server.annotations.ExposeEntity</filename>
      annotation. The presence of this annotation will cause Errai's GWT
      compiler extensions to generate marshall/demarshall stubs for the
      annotated objects at compile-time.</para>

      <para>For example:</para>

      <programlisting>

@ExposeEntity
public class User implements java.io.Serializable {
    private int userId;

    public int getUserId() {
        return userId;
    }

    public void setUserId(int userId) {
        this.userId = userId;
    }
 [...]
}
      </programlisting>

      <note>
        <para>All exposed entities must follow the <ulink
        url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/JavaBean">java bean
        convention</ulink></para>
      </note>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="wiring">
      <title>Wiring server side components</title>

      <para>Currently, ErraiBus uses Google Guice to wire components. However,
      we plan on falling back on the <emphasis>JSR-330 Dependency
      Injection</emphasis> specification in the near future. When deploying
      services on the server-side, it is currently possible to obtain
      references to the <filename>MessageBus</filename>,
      <filename>RequestDispatcher</filename>, the
      <filename>ErraiServiceConfigurator</filename>, and
      <filename>ErraiService</filename> by declaring them as injection
      dependencies in Service classes, extension components, and session
      providers.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>Bus configuration</title>

      <para><emphasis>Note: The details in this section are currently subject
      to change. Please consult this section if you are working off
      pre-release versions of ErraiBus.</emphasis></para>

      <sect2>
        <title>web.xml and app server configuration</title>

        <para>Depending on what application server you are deploying on, you
        must provide an appropriate servlet implementation if you wish to use
        true, asynchronous I/O.</para>

        <para>Here's a sample web.xml file:</para>

        <programlisting>&lt;web-app xmlns="http://java.sun.com/xml/ns/javaee"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://java.sun.com/xml/ns/javaee
		  http://java.sun.com/xml/ns/javaee/web-app_2_5.xsd"
         version="2.5"&gt;

    &lt;servlet&gt;
        &lt;servlet-name&gt;ErraiServlet&lt;/servlet-name&gt;
        &lt;servlet-class&gt;org.jboss.errai.bus.server.servlet.DefaultBlockingServlet&lt;/servlet-class&gt;
        &lt;load-on-startup&gt;1&lt;/load-on-startup&gt;
    &lt;/servlet&gt;

    &lt;servlet-mapping&gt;
        &lt;servlet-name&gt;ErraiServlet&lt;/servlet-name&gt;
        &lt;url-pattern&gt;*.erraiBus&lt;/url-pattern&gt;
    &lt;/servlet-mapping&gt;

    &lt;context-param&gt;
        &lt;param-name&gt;errai.properties&lt;/param-name&gt;
        &lt;param-value&gt;/WEB-INF/errai.properties&lt;/param-value&gt;
    &lt;/context-param&gt;

    &lt;context-param&gt;
        &lt;param-name&gt;login.config&lt;/param-name&gt;
        &lt;param-value&gt;/WEB-INF/login.config&lt;/param-value&gt;
    &lt;/context-param&gt;

    &lt;context-param&gt;
        &lt;param-name&gt;users.properties&lt;/param-name&gt;
        &lt;param-value&gt;/WEB-INF/users.properties&lt;/param-value&gt;
    &lt;/context-param&gt;

&lt;/web-app&gt;</programlisting>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="bus-config">
        <title>ErraiService.properties</title>

        <para>The ErraiService.properties file contains basic configuration
        for the bus itself.</para>

        <para>Example Configuration:</para>

        <programlisting>
##
## Request dispatcher implementation (default is SimpleDispatcher)
##
#errai.dispatcher_implementation=org.jboss.errai.bus.server.SimpleDispatcher
errai.dispatcher_implementation=org.jboss.errai.bus.server.AsyncDispatcher


#
## Worker pool size.  This is the number of threads the asynchronous worker pool should provide for processing
## incoming messages. This option is only valid when using the AsyncDispatcher implementation.
##
errai.async.thread_pool_size=5

##
## Worker timeout (in seconds).  This defines the time that a single asychronous process may run, before the worker pool
## terminates it and reclaims the thread.   This option is only valid when using the AsyncDispatcher implementation.
##
errai.async.worker.timeout=5

##
## Specify the Authentication/Authorization Adapter to use
##
#errai.authentication_adapter=org.jboss.errai.persistence.server.security.HibernateAuthenticationAdapter
#errai.authentication_adapter=org.jboss.errai.bus.server.security.auth.JAASAdapter

##
## This property indicates whether or not authentication is required for all communication with the bus.  Set this
## to 'true' if all access to your application should be secure.
##
#errai.require_authentication_for_all=true



</programlisting>

        <sect3>
          <title>errai.dispatcher_implementation</title>

          <para>The <filename>errai.dispatcher_implementation</filename>
          defines, as it's name quite succinctly implies, the dispatcher
          implementation to be used by the bus. There are two implementations
          which come with Errai out of the box: the
          <filename>SimpleDispatcher</filename> and the
          <filename>AsyncDispatcher</filename>. See section on Dispatchers for
          more information about the differences between the two.</para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3>
          <title>errai.async_thread_pool_size</title>

          <para>Specifies the total number of worker threads in the worker
          pool for handling and delivering messages. Adjusting this value does
          not have any effect if you are using the SimpleDispatcher.</para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3>
          <title>errai.async_worker.timeout</title>

          <para>Specifies the total amount of a time (in seconds) a service
          has to finish processing an incoming message before the pool
          interrupts the thread and returns an error. Adjusting this value
          does not have an effect if you are using the
          SimpleDispatcher.</para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3>
          <title>errai.authentication_adapter</title>

          <para>Specifies the authentication adapter the bus should use for
          determining whether calls should be serviced based on authentication
          and security principles.</para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3>
          <title>errai.require_authentication_for_all</title>

          <para>Indicates whether or not the bus should always require the use
          of authentication for all requests inbound for the bus. If this is
          turned on, an authentication adapter must be defined, and any user
          must be authenticated before the bus will deliver any messages from
          the client to any service.</para>
        </sect3>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>ErraiApp.properties</title>

        <para>The ErraiApp.properties is a marker file. It does not contain
        any configuration, but it is required that it be present in any module
        you wish Errai to scan for deployable extensions and services. It
        should be located as the top-level directory of any JAR or
        Directory-based module.</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>

  <!---
        =====================================================
        QUICKSTART
        =====================================================
    -->

  <chapter id="workspaces">
    <title>Errai Workspaces</title>

    <sect1>
      <title>What is workspaces?</title>

      <para>ErraiWorkspaces provides a fully managed working UI enviroment for
      which to deploy your console and tooling. Put more succinctly: we
      provide you the places. All you need to do is put stuff there.</para>

      <sect2>
        <title>Basic concepts</title>

        <para>It's good to start with an explanation of the basic workspace
        concepts and terminlogy that we chose for it.</para>

        <para>A workspace, in our term, is basically a collection of tools.
        Each tool serves a distinct purpose and can represent anything you
        like. The workspace manages the tools (or tool sets) and access to
        them. This includes loading and initialization, history, preferences
        and authorization amongst other things. Usually tools rely on the
        message bus for inter component communication as well as backend
        integration. But they are not tight to that. Workspaces makes no
        assumption about the implementation of your tool, it merely provides
        the glue to keep everything together.</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>Sandbox</title>

        <para>Workspaces goes beyond simple API. It's not just another GWT
        module. It was designed to get you started quickly, without getting in
        your way. This includes the environment to build, deploy and test your
        tools. We've decided to use maven to provide these capabilities. It
        allows you to quickly get started (see <link
        linkend="quickstart">Maven archetype</link>), but more importantly,
        maven repositories are used to share tool implementations across
        workspace assemblies. This way you can easily combine your own and 3rd
        party tools as part of a custom workspace compilation. <note>
            <para>The GWT SDK is already part of the sandbox bootstrap. You
            get everything to get going within minutes: GWT, Errai and 3rd
            party libraries.</para>
          </note></para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="workspace-api">
      <title>Workspace API</title>

      <para>To begin with, we'll look at some examples how to declare tool
      sets and launch them in a workspace.</para>

      <sect2>
        <title>Declaring and implementing tools</title>

        <para>Tools are declared through the @LoadToolSet annotation. This
        instructs the workspace to generate all the boiler plate to wire your
        tools with the workspace. A tool needs to implement the WidgetProvider
        interface. It's used by the workspace to instruct the tool to create
        it's UI widget when needed. This widget will then be embedded in the
        workspace. <programlisting>
@LoadTool(name = "Users", group = "Administration")                          (1)
public class UserManagement implements WidgetProvider
{

  public void provideWidget(final ProvisioningCallback callback) {           (2)
    callback.onSuccess(new UserManagementWidget());
  }

  class UserManagementWidget extends LayoutPanel                             (3)
  {
      [...]
  }
}
  </programlisting> <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Toolset declaration including the name and group this tool
              belongs to</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>The WidgetProvider implementation is manadatory.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>In this example our widget is LayoutPanel with unknown
              contents. The implementation is up to you.</para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist></para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="rolebased">
        <title>Authorization and access to tools</title>

        <para>Workspaces relies on a authentication scheme similiar to JAAS.
        It ships with different authentication modules (i.e. Hibernate, JAAS)
        that enable role based access to tools on the client side and services
        on the server side. <programlisting>
@LoadTool(name = "Inventory", group = "Administration")                (1)
@RequireRoles({"admin"})                                               (2)
public class Inventory implements WidgetProvider
{

    public void provideWidget(final ProvisioningCallback callback)     (3)
    {
        [...]
    }

}

</programlisting> <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>A tool declaration</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>It restricts access to the role 'admin'</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Implements the default WidgetProvider interface which will
              only be invoked when the principal is authorized to access this
              tool.</para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist></para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>Common coding pattern</title>

        <para>It's common to use the WidgetProvider API in a way that <ulink
        url="http://code.google.com/p/google-web-toolkit/wiki/CodeSplitting">GWT
        2.0 code splitting</ulink> can kick in. This allows true lazy loading
        of tools upon demand, including all .js and resources necessary to run
        your tools: <programlisting>
@LoadTool(name = "Group Tasks", group = "Tasks")
public class OpenTasksModule implements WidgetProvider
{
    static OpenTasksView instance = null;

    public void provideWidget(final ProvisioningCallback callback)
    {
        GWT.runAsync(
            new RunAsyncCallback()
            {
              public void onFailure(Throwable err)
              {
                GWT.log("Failed to load tool", err);
              }

              public void onSuccess()
              {
                if (instance == null) {
                  instance = new OpenTasksView();  // your tool here
                }
                callback.onSuccess(instance);
              }
            }

        );
    }
}

</programlisting></para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>Core features</title>

      <para>The workspace itself doesn't require any attention apart from the
      common API that is decribed in the chapter <link
      linkend="workspace-api">"Workspace API"</link>. Still, in some cases you
      may need to go beyond the out-of-the-box functionlity. In this chapter
      we are going to explain the building blocks used in the workspace
      implementation and how they can be used to replace or extend the default
      workspace behaviour.</para>

      <sect2 id="workspace-registry">
        <title>Workspace Registry</title>

        <para>The workspace registry
        (org.jboss.errai.workspaces.client.framework.Registry) is a simple all
        purpose lookup for common workspace API that is available to any
        workspace component: <programlisting>
AuthenticationContext authenticationContext =
    Registry.get(SecurityService.class).getAuthenticationContext();
</programlisting></para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>Security</title>

        <para>The workspace itself doesn't provide an authentication
        component. Instead it relies on the Authentication provided by errai
        bus. When the workspace is loaded two thing happen: The workspace
        checks if authentication is required and, after authentication if
        needed, loads the tool sets.</para>

        <para>The bus component in charge is the SecurityService
        (org.jboss.errai.bus.client.security.SecurityService). It is available
        through <link linkend="workspace-registry">workspace Registry</link>.
        For people extending the workspace functionality it offers two
        intersting options: <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Obtain access to the authentication context (username,
              roles, etc)</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Deferred workspace assembly</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist> The later is important of you want to provide your
        own way of authenticating users, but still use the <link
        linkend="rolebased">role based authorization</link> build into
        workspaces. <note>
            <para>Don't mess with the authentication unless you now what you
            are doing. In many cases it might be better to extend the server
            side authentication adapters instead of overriding the client
            behaviour. However for the sake of completeness, this mechanism
            should be mentioned here.</para>
          </note></para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>Authentication and Authorization</title>

        <para>The LoginClient is the counter part of the SecurityService. It
        is instructed by the SecurityService to request the credentials upon
        demand. This typically happens when the workspace is initialized, but
        might also occur later on, when a particular service requires a
        different role set, then the one assigned initially. We call this
        elevation. Similiar to the operating system of your choice that
        demands administrator priviledges for certain operations.</para>

        <para>After the initial authentication (or lack of) the LoginClient
        instructs the actual workspace to assemble the tool sets.</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>History management and perma links</title>

        <para>History is build into the workspace. It's wired to the main
        navigation and allows to use the browser navigation to switch between
        previously selected tools. In addition to that, the same mechanism can
        be used to perma link tools from external applications. I.e. when
        notifying users, using an email that contains a link back to a
        particular tool.</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>Preferences</title>

        <para>The workspace allows you to store simple key-value pairs as
        preferences. Like with other common API, you obtain the Preferences
        through the <link linkend="workspace-registry">workspace
        Registry</link>:
            <programlisting>
Preferences prefs = Registry.get(Preferences.class);
prefs.set("default_sort_order", "ASC");
            </programlisting>

            The default implementation uses a cookie based
        approach, but it's easy to replace that one with a custom
        implementation in the module decriptor: <programlisting>

   &lt;module&gt;
    [...]
    &lt;replace-with class="org.jboss.errai.workspaces.client.framework.CookiePreferences"&gt;
           &lt;when-type-is class="org.jboss.errai.workspaces.client.framework.Preferences"/&gt;
       &lt;/replace-with&gt;
    &lt;/module&gt;

</programlisting></para>
      </sect2>

         <sect2>
        <title>Logging</title>
        <para>
            Workspaces inherits <ulink url="http://code.google.com/p/gwt-log/">GWT Log</ulink>.
            It ships with an embedded log message console that records log output, besides the default logging
            to the browser error console and the GWT hosted mode window. To use the internal logging mechanism,
            simply write messages to the Logger:            
            <programlisting>
import com.allen_sauer.gwt.log.client.Log;
 [...]

Log.warn("some log message");
Log.error("message", throwable);
                
            </programlisting>

        </para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="using-workspaces">
      <title>Building a workspaces application</title>

      <para>In this section we go through the steps necessary to create a
      workspace application. As mentioned before, workspaces is more then just
      another GWT library. It's intended to get you started quickly. This
      includes GWT installation, creating a build environment and prepapring
      your IDE.</para>

      <sect2>
        <title>Check the prerequisites</title>

        <para>You need <ulink url="http://maven.apache.org">Apache
        Maven</ulink> and a <ulink
        url="http://java.sun.com/javase/downloads/index.jsp">JDK</ulink> to
        get started.</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>Setup a build environent</title>

        <para>The most simple (and least error prone) way to get started is
        using the maven archetype that we ship as part of errai. Simply follow
        the instructions in the <link linkend="quickstart">quickstart</link>
        section and return here when you are done.</para>

        <para>Once you've created a project using the maven archetype, make
        yourself familiar with the directory structure: <programlisting>
Laika:gwt-app hbraun$ lstree
| pom.xml
|-src
|---main
|-----java
|-------foo
|---------bar
|-----------client
|-----------server
|-war
|---WEB-INF
</programlisting> It basically follows the default GWT guidelines for breaking
        up code between client and server. Simply put tools (@LoadToolSet)
        into the client subpackage and services (@Service) into the server
        subpackages. Make sure you are familiar with the <link
        linkend="workspace-api">Workspace API</link> before you
        continue.</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>Verify the application configuration</title>

        <para>Several configuration files drive a workspace build and the
        final application. Make sure to include all of them when porting the
        archetype example to a different GWT application: <programlisting>
 ./src/main/java/ErraiApp.properties
 ./src/main/java/ErraiService.properties
 ./src/main/java/my/app/App.gwt.xml
</programlisting> <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>ErraiApp.properties is a simple marker, that is required
              for the annotation processing to discover your modules. This is
              especially important when you declare maven dependencies on tool
              or service implementations. Make sure that any classpath entry
              (i.e. dependency jar) contains an ErraiApp.properties file.
              Otherwise errai might not be able to discover your
              components.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>ErraiService.properties is the primary bus configuration.
              Details can be found in the chapter <link
              linkend="bus-config">bus configuration.</link></para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>App.gwt.xml is your applications <ulink
              url="http://code.google.com/webtoolkit/doc/latest/DevGuideOrganizingProjects.html#DevGuideModules">module
              descriptor</ulink>. <programlisting>

&lt;module rename-to="app"&gt;
 &lt;inherits name='com.google.gwt.user.User'/&gt;
 &lt;inherits name="com.google.gwt.uibinder.UiBinder"/&gt;
 &lt;inherits name="com.google.gwt.resources.Resources" /&gt;

 &lt;inherits name="org.jboss.errai.common.ErraiCommon"/&gt;
 &lt;inherits name="org.jboss.errai.bus.ErraiBus"/&gt;
 &lt;inherits name="org.jboss.errai.workspaces.ErraiWorkspaces" /&gt;

 &lt;entry-point class='my.app.client.HelloWorldClient'/&gt;

&lt;/module&gt;

</programlisting> If you are building on workspaces make sure to include it's
              dependencies common and bus as well.</para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist></para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>Launch the hosted mode and start developing</title>

        <para>If you followed the steps above, and did build your application
        stub using the maven archetype, then you should be launch the <ulink
        url="http://code.google.com/webtoolkit/doc/latest/DevGuideCompilingAndDebugging.html#DevGuideDevMode">GWT
        hosted mode</ulink> with the following commands: <programlisting>
  mvn gwt:run

 (alternatively)
  mvn gwt:debug
</programlisting> <note>
            <title>Launching maven the first time</title>

            <para>Please note, that when launching maven the first time on
            your machine, it will fetch all dependecies from a central
            repository. This may take a while, because it includes downloading
            large binaries like GWT SDK. However subsequent builds are not
            required to go through this step and will be much faster.</para>
          </note></para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>

    <!---
        =====================================================
        WORKING WITH ERRAI
        =====================================================
    -->


    <chapter id="working_with_errai">
        <title>Working with Errai</title>

        <sect1>
            <title>Debug facilities</title>
            <para>
                Debugging message oriented systems can easily become a complex task.
                Messages are being published and consumed all across your application components
                and the choreography (exchange pattern) is not obvious at a first glance.
                You cannot simply step through an IDE, following typed references that explain how the code flows
                and in which order components are invoked.
            </para>

            <para>
                We are constantly trying to improve the facilities that assist you with these task.
                The most important ones are described in the next sections.
            </para>

            <sect2>
                <title>Visual Bus Monitor</title>
                <para>
                    Errai ships with Swing-based ErraiBus Monitor application. It's really straight-forward to get up and running.
                    You simply add it as a runtime dependency, and bootstrap GWT Development Mode with the
<programlisting>
    -Derrai.tools.bus_monitor_attach=true
</programlisting>
                    VM flag, and this magical UI should automatically appear as ErraiBus bootstraps.
                    When the monitor is activated, it attaches probes in into the bus and records all activity accordingly.
                    You can drill down into individual services and examine individual messages that have been received to debug any mysterious problems that arise.                     

                </para>

                <para>
                    <figure id="bus_monitor">
                        <title>Bus Monitor</title>
                        <mediaobject>
                            <imageobject>
                                <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/monitor.png"/>
                            </imageobject>
                        </mediaobject>
                    </figure>

                </para>
                <para>                    
                    The monitor allows you to inspect the endpoints (aka 'subjects') registred on any client connected
                    to the system and the server side services as well. This should already give an idea how the messaging
                    landscape is layed out. However, be aware that some endpoints may be registered lazily, i.e. when
                    a UI component is loaded. This is especially true for <link linkend="workspaces">Errai Workspaces</link>, which
                    tends load complete toolsets lazily (<ulink url="http://code.google.com/p/google-web-toolkit/wiki/CodeSplitting">GWT code splitting</ulink>).
                </para>
            </sect2>

        </sect1>

        <sect1>
            <title>Proxied access to external containers</title>
            <para>
            Usually GWT developement happens in hosted mode and then, later on, the GWT app
            is turned into a webapp (*.war) that can be deployed on a target container (app server, servlet engine).
            This works quiet well for closed systems that don't depend on additional resources the target container
            provides. A typical resource would be a DataSource for access to a relational database. 
            </para>

            <para>
                Instead of pulling these resources into the hosted mode servlet engine (jetty, read-only JNDI)
                or creating mock objects for any resources that cannot be run in hosted mode, we offer you a much more simple
                way to develop with errai: Simply proxy all requests that occur in hosted mode to an external target container:
                <figure id="proxy">
                    <title>Development Proxy</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/proxy.png"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>

            </para>

            <para>
               The proxy is implemented a yet another servlet that you need to add to the web.xml
               that's being sed in hosted mode:
<programlisting>
&lt;servlet>
    &lt;servlet-name>erraiProxy&lt;/servlet-name>
    &lt;description>Errai Proxy&lt;/description>
    &lt;servlet-class>org.jboss.errai.tools.proxy.XmlHttpProxyServlet&lt;/servlet-class>
        &lt;init-param>
            &lt;param-name>config.name&lt;/param-name>
            &lt;param-value>errai-proxy.json&lt;/param-value>      (1)
        &lt;/init-param>
        &lt;load-on-startup>1&lt;/load-on-startup>
&lt;/servlet>
               
&lt;servlet-mapping>
    &lt;servlet-name>erraiProxy&lt;/servlet-name>
    &lt;url-pattern>/app/proxy/*&lt;/url-pattern>                  (2)
&lt;/servlet-mapping>
           
</programlisting>
            <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Proxy configuration. See details below.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>The proxy url pattern convetion. The bus bootstraps on this URL.</para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>
            </para>

            <para>
                The web.xml proxy declaration contains two notable elements: A reference to
                the proxy configuration file and a URL pattern, where the proxy can found.
                While the later shouldn't be changed (the bus bootstraps on this URL),
                you need to change the proxy config according to your needs:
<programlisting>
 {"xhp": {
    "version": "1.1",
    "services": [
        {"id": "default",
         "url":"http://127.0.0.1:8080/my-gwt-app/in.erraiBus",
         "passthrough":true
        },
    ]
  }
}
</programlisting>
                You would need to <emphasis>change the host, port and webcontext</emphasis> ('my-gwt-app' in this case)
                to reflect the location of the external container. 'passthrough' simply means that any
                request to 'proxy/in.erraiBus' will go to 'container/my-gwt-app/in.erraiBus'.

                This already indicates that you need to have the server side part of your GWT application,
                already running on the target container. The most simple way to achieve this, is to build a
                the complete webapp, deploy it and ignore the UI parts that may be available on the server.               
            </para>
        </sect1>

    </chapter>

    <!---
        =====================================================
        QUICKSTART
        =====================================================
    -->

  <chapter id="quickstart">
    <title>Appendix A: Quickstart</title>

    <section id="quickstart-intro">
      <title>Using the maven archetype</title>

      <para>If you have taken a look at the examples that ship with the
      distribution, you realized that we use maven to build them. The way it
      is setup, the maven build has several benefits: <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>It pulls the GWT from a central repository. No need for
            manual installation of the SDK</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>It provides us with the proper dependencies in order to run
            the examples</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>IDE setup is greatly simplfied, since most modern IDE's can
            directly import the maven structure</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist> In order to get you going quickly, we've provided a
      project archetype, that allows you to create a project skeleton similiar
      to the one we use for building the examples. It's based on the maven
      archetype plugin <footnote>
          <para>http://maven.apache.org/plugins/maven-archetype-plugin/</para>
        </footnote> and needs to be invoked from the command line:
      <programlisting>
    mvn archetype:generate \
        -DarchetypeGroupId=org.jboss.errai \
        -DarchetypeArtifactId=sandbox-archetype \
        -DarchetypeVersion=1.1-SNAPSHOT \
        -DarchetypeRepository=https://repository.jboss.org/nexus/content/groups/public/
            </programlisting> When invoking the archetype build it ask you
      about the maven groupId, artifactId and package name your GWT
      application should use: <programlisting>
    Define value for groupId: : <emphasis>foo.bar</emphasis>
    Define value for artifactId: : <emphasis>gwt-app</emphasis>
    Define value for version:  1.0-SNAPSHOT: :
    Define value for package:  foo.bar: : <emphasis>foo.bar.ui</emphasis>
    Confirm properties configuration:
    groupId: foo.bar
    artifactId: gwt-app
    version: 1.0-SNAPSHOT
    package: foo.bar.ui
    Y: : <emphasis>Y</emphasis>
            </programlisting> What will be created for you, is a maven build
      structure, including references to the GWT SDK and the Errai
      dependencies necessary to launch a simple application: <programlisting>
    Laika:test hbraun$ cd gwt-app/
    Laika:gwt-app hbraun$ lstree
    |-src
    |---main
    |-----java
    |-------foo
    |---------bar
    |-----------client
    |-----------server
    |-war
    |---WEB-INF
            </programlisting> In order launch the GWT hosted mode, change into
      the project directory and type: <programlisting>
    mvn gwt:run
            </programlisting> The default project includes both a HelloWorld
      client (GWT), and a HelloWorld service.</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>
</book>
