<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="sid-9470155">
    
    <title>Errai CDI Maven Archetype</title>
    <para>
      The different runtime models explained
      <ulink url="https://docs.jboss.org/author/pages/viewpage.action?pageId=5931501">here</ulink>
      are all incorporated into this maven archetype using profiles. It enables execution in Development Mode and supports both packaging for deployment to a Servlet Engine and the JBoss Application Server.
    </para>
    <para>To begin with we'll create a project layout using a maven build structure, which will provide us with a bare bones project, including all dependencies, which can later on be imported in your IDE of choice.</para>
    <informalexample>
      <programlisting>
mvn archetype:generate \
-DarchetypeGroupId=org.jboss.errai.archetypes \
-DarchetypeArtifactId=cdi-quickstart \
-DarchetypeVersion=2.2.0.CR1 \
-DarchetypeRepository=https://repository.jboss.org/nexus/content/groups/public/
</programlisting>
    </informalexample>
    <para>Customize the build properties according to your needs.</para>
    <informalexample>
      <programlisting>
Define value for property 'groupId': : foo.bar
Define value for property 'artifactId': : gwt-app
Define value for property 'version': 1.0-SNAPSHOT:
Define value for property 'package': foo.bar: com.foo.bar
Confirm properties configuration:
groupId: foo.bar
artifactId: gwt-app
version: 1.0-SNAPSHOT
package: com.foo.bar
Y:
</programlisting>
    </informalexample>
    <para>The project will be created in a directory that corresponds to the provided artifactId.</para>
    <para>In a few simple steps, you have created a build environment that can build, test, package, and launch a simple application. You can now launch GWT development mode, run integration tests with coverage reporting, and package your web application for deployment.</para>
    <para>To launch the GWT development mode, change into the project directory (name corresponding to the provided artifactId) and type:</para>
    <informalexample>
      <programlisting>
mvn gwt:run (launch hosted mode)
mvn gwt:debug (launch hosted with debug settings)
</programlisting>
    </informalexample>
    <para>The example application comes with an integration test suite that exercises most of its client-side and server-side code. To run the test suite, type:</para>
    <informalexample>
      <programlisting>mvn test -Pintegration-test</programlisting>
    </informalexample>
    <para>To generate a set of HTML documents under target/site/jacoco/ detailing code coverage of the most recent test run, type:</para>
    <informalexample>
      <programlisting>mvn site</programlisting>
    </informalexample>
    <para>
      By default the archetype does package the web application for Development Mode execution. To deploy your application to JBoss AS 7, you need to execute a clean rebuild using the JBoss profile (e.g.
      <code>-Pjboss7</code>
      ).
    </para>
    <informalexample>
      <programlisting>
mvn -Pjboss7 clean install
cp target/gwt-app.war $JBOSS_HOME/standalone/deployments
</programlisting>
    </informalexample>
    <note>
      <title>Importing the project into eclipse</title>
      <para>
        The setup instuctions for eclipse can be found in the Errai
        <ulink url="http://community.jboss.org/wiki/WorkingwithGWTCDIandErrai">WIKI</ulink>
        .
      </para>
    </note>
  </chapter>
