<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="sid-9470150">
    
    <title>Errai Maven Archetype</title>
    <para>
      In order to get you going quickly, we've provided a project archetype, that allows you to create a project skeleton similiar to the one we use for building the examples. It's based on the maven archetype plugin
      <ulink url="http://maven.apache.org/plugins/maven-archetype-plugin/"/>
      and needs to be invoked from the command line:
    </para>
    <informalexample>
      <programlisting>
mvn archetype:generate \
-DarchetypeGroupId=org.jboss.errai.archetypes \
-DarchetypeArtifactId=bus-quickstart \
-DarchetypeVersion=2.2.0.CR1 \
-DarchetypeRepository=https://repository.jboss.org/nexus/content/groups/public/
</programlisting>
    </informalexample>
    <para>When invoking the archetype build you will be asked to provide the maven groupId, artifactId and package name your GWT application should use:</para>
    <informalexample>
      <programlisting>
Define value for groupId: : foo.bar
Define value for artifactId: : gwt-app
Define value for version: 1.0-SNAPSHOT: :
Define value for package: foo.bar: : foo.bar.ui
Confirm properties configuration:
groupId: foo.bar
artifactId: gwt-app
version: 1.0-SNAPSHOT
package: foo.bar.ui
Y: :
</programlisting>
    </informalexample>
    <para>You will be left with a maven build structure, including references to the GWT SDK and the Errai dependencies necessary to build, test, package, and launch a simple application.</para>
    <para>To launch the GWT development mode, change into the project directory (name corresponding to the provided artifactId) and type:</para>
    <informalexample>
      <programlisting>mvn gwt:run</programlisting>
    </informalexample>
    <para>The example application also comes with an integration test suite that exercises most of its client-side and server-side code. To run the test suite, type:</para>
    <informalexample>
      <programlisting>mvn test -Pintegration-test</programlisting>
    </informalexample>
    <para>To generate a set of HTML documents under target/site/jacoco/ detailing code coverage of the most recent test run, type:</para>
    <informalexample>
      <programlisting>mvn site</programlisting>
    </informalexample>
    <para>
      By default the archetype does package the web application for Development Mode execution. To deploy your application to JBoss AS 7, you need to execute a clean rebuild using the JBoss profile (e.g.
      <code>-Pjboss7</code>
      ).
    </para>
    <informalexample>
      <programlisting>
mvn -Pjboss7 clean install
cp target/gwt-app.war $JBOSS_HOME/standalone/deployments
</programlisting>
    </informalexample>
  </chapter>
